Guide to the Playing Card and Game Collection 1549-present (Bulk 1800-1899) PR 115
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
- Series III. German and Austrian Playing Cards
  - Metamorphosen der Neuzeit für Knaben; Modern transformations for boys, [1850] (Box 9, Folder 38)
  - Pariser Metamorphosen. Frauenköpfe; Paris Metamorphoses. Female head, [1850] (Box 10, Folder 39-40)
  - Robert Blum, [1851] (Box 10, Folder 41-42)
  - Robert Blum (with separately boxed container), [1851] (Box 10, Folder 43)
  - [Mini Pink Pack], [1852] (Box 10, Folder 44)
  - Die Hochzeit auf dem Lande/La Noce De Village, [1855] (Box 10, Folder 45)
  - Der Christmarkt -- ein neues frag und antwortspiel für angenehmen und nützlichen Unterhaltung No. 69, [1858] (Box 10, Folder 46)
  - Biedermeier (with separately boxed container), [1860] (Box 10, Folder 47)
  - Bilder Zaubereien fur Jung und Alt, [1860] (Box 10, Folder 48)
  - Das Orakel oder des Errathen fremder Gedanken/L'oracle ou l'art de deviner les pensèes desautres No. 81, [1860] (Box 10, Folder 49)
  - [Fetscher deck - opened, blue], [1860] (Box 10, Folder 50)
  - [Fetscher deck - sealed, red], [1860] (Box 10, Folder 51)
  - [Fetscher deck - sealed, blue], [1860] (Box 10, Folder 52)
  - [Translucent Deck] (with separately boxed container), [1860] (Box 11, Folder 53)
  - Franz Josef, 1863 (Box 11, Folder 54)
  - FrankfurtschUtzenkarten, 1864 (Box 11, Folder 55)
  - Franz Josef, [1865] (Box 11, Folder 56)
  - Ausschlagspiel zur Unterhaltung in 52 Blatter und in 4 sprachen, [1870] (Box 11, Folder 57)
  - [Fromman & Bunte's Transformation Deck] [square corners], [1870] (Box 11, Folder 58)
  - [Fromman & Bunte's Transformation Deck] [round corners], [1870] (Box 11, Folder 59)
  - Schweizer Karter, [1884] (Box 11, Folder 60)
  - Scherzhastes Frag und Antwort Spiel mit 25 blättern/Jeu Amusant de Questions et de Responses an 25 Feuilles, [1890] (Box 11, Folder 61)
  - JFK Playing Cards featuring President Kennedy and family, 2004 (Box 11, Folder 62)
    Scope and Contents Note
    manufactured in the EU for Piatnik, Vienna.
- Series IV. French Playing Cards
  Series IV. spans the years from 1668 to 1901 and contains 41 card decks and games. Cards are ordered by date and thereunder alphabetically by name or subject. Cards with known dates always come before those with circa dates.
  The multiple packs of "French pre-Revolutionary cards" often had a secondary usage. For example, "French pre-Revolutionary cards #2a" has the lingerie accounts of a Mme. Marugal on the verso. Other cards have been used to clip other pieces of paper together or to help children learn the alphabet.
  "Les Jeu des Fables" are three slotted books for metamorphosis-style game. Cards fit into each slot and can combine to make humorous combinations. "[Opaque Translucent cards]" show erotic scenes, but the hidden images are not as easy to discern as in the German and Spanish decks.
  "[Multi-themed court cards]" is a very unusual deck. Each suit carries a different thematic motif. The hearts portray love, the spades military life, the clubs flowers, and the diamonds construction or labor. The ace of diamonds features nude men, figures usually scarce in card deck designs.
  - [Character game with dice], undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - [French pre-revolutionary cards #1-#6], undated (Box 11, Folder 2-7)
  - [French pre-revolutionary cards #7] (with separately boxed container), undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - [French pre-revolutionary cards #8-#12], undated (Box 12, Folder 9-13)
  - [French teaching cards], undated (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - [Le Normand style fortune-telling deck], undated (Box 12, Folder 15-17)
  - [Lequart's Tarot], undated (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - [Tarot cards], undated (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Jeu de Blason, [1668] (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - [Seventeenth century French courts], [1680] (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - [Italian/Spanish/French Tarot], 1762 (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Poule de Henri IV, [1792] (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - [Sybille des salons (?)], [1800] (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Grand Jeu Des Fables Choises avec Figures Coloriès, [1805] (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Huiteme Jeu de Cartes Historiques, [1809] (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Tableaux de la Gèographie Dè diè a la Jeunèsse, [1810] (Box 13, Folder 27)
  - [Uncut-Metamorphosis-1], [1820] (Box 13, Folder 28)
  - [Uncut-Metamorphosis-2], [1820] (Box 13, Folder 29)
  - Le Jeu des Fables (series A), [1820] (Box 13, Folder 30)
  - Le Jeu des Fables (series C), [1820] (Box 13, Folder 31)
  - Le Jeu des Fables (series D), [1820] (Box 13, Folder 32)
  - Paiements au Boston de Fontainbleau; Règle du jeu de Boston, [1820] (Box 13, Folder 33)
  - [Street cries or Cries of Paris], [1830] (Box 13, Folder 34)
  - [Hand-drawn transformation], [1840] (Box 13, Folder 35)
  - [Opaque Translucent cards], [1840] (Box 13, Folder 36)
  - [Theater of Napoleon], [1845] (Box 13, Folder 37)
  - Casse Tete D'architecture, [1850] (Box 13, Folder 38)
  - [Black-and-tan fortune-telling deck], [1890] (Box 13, Folder 39)
  - [Mini LeNormand style fortune-telling deck], [1890] (Box 13, Folder 40)
  - Le Jeu des Repertoires, [1901] (Box 13, Folder 41)
- Series V. Other Playing Cards
  Series V. dates from 1699 to 2000. This series contains 24 card decks from Belgium, Czechoslovakia, Hong Kong, Hungary, Italy, the Netherlands, Spain, and Switzerland. It also includes a "millenium deck" printed by the International Playing Card Society and given to the New-York Historical Society when the organization met in New York City in 2000.
  "[Spanish translucent cards]" is the only known pack of erotic cards to have been made with Spanish suit signs, although this deck is not the sole copy.
  Cards in this series were published in: Prague, Czechoslovakia; Pest, Hungary; Urbino, Milan, and Trevizo, Italy; Madrid, Barcelona, and Igualda, Spain; and Neuchatel, Switzerland. See the database for more information on the decks' creation.
  Cards are ordered by country of origin and thereunder by date and then alphabetically by name or subject. Cards with known dates always come before those with circa dates.
  - Belgian Cards
    - [Mogul Cards], undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - [Mini Belgian deck], [1875] (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Czechoslovakian Cards
    - Zauberschleier, Wastl und Welt - umsegler, 1843 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Dutch Cards
    - Tiresias voorzeggende Kaarten Almanack, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Loterijspel, [1815] (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - A.B.C. En Geschenk voor Lieve Kindere, [1855] (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Hong Kong Cards
    - [Mini Hong Kong deck], [1973] (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Hungarian Cards
    - [Tarocchini from Pest], undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Italian Cards
    - [Albani], [1699] (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - [Eighteenth century deck from Naples], [1750] (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - [Gumppenberg's Tarot], [1838] (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - [Preziozo], [1866] (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Spanish Cards
    - [Rf. Fa. DEMd. Ano OE 1801] (Box 14, Folder 13-14)
    - [Anton Lombart, Barcelona], 1825 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - [Spanish translucent cards], 1877 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - [Girbau y Audinis, Igualda], [1885] (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Swiss Cards
    - [Tarot from Bern], undated (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - [C.F. Dreyspring Tarrocchini], 1801 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - [Rochias Tarocchini], 1816 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - [Game of marriages], [1840] (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - The lottery of traders, [1840] (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - [Schaffhouse Tarot], [1860] (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Other Cards
    - [IPCS Millenium Deck], 2000 (Box 14, Folder 24)
- Oversized Cards
  - From Series II. British Playing Cards
    - The Cries of London, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - The Game of Pastora or the Shephardess of the Pyrenees, 1796 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - From Series III. German and Austrian Playing Cards
    - ["Stukeley's" cards, after those in the British Museum], 1546 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Naturgemählde, undated (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Das Uhr - und Stundenspiel; Le Jeu d'horloge et des heures, undated (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Jeden Lappen gefallt seine Kappen, [1830] (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - Fünfzig deutsche Bilder Räthsel, hieroglyphen Calembours und rebus(instructions), [1845] (Box 15, Folder 32)
    - Der Kampf um die Braut; Le Combat pour la Fiancée, [1850] (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Metamorphosen der Neuzeit für Knaben; Modern transformations for boys, [1850] (Box 15, Folder 38)
  - From Series IV. French Playing Cards
    - Poule de Henri IV, [1792] (Box 15, Folder 23)
  - From Series III. German and Austrian Playing Cards
    - ["Stukeley's" cards, after those in the British Museum], 1546 (Box 16, Folder 9)